Hello everyone and welcome to a new IBMI
RPA sample video. Today I'd like to talk
to you about the data gen up code and
about the generator called multi RPL
that I found on RP cafe that uses data
gen to substitute several values into a
string and then I will show you how we
can use this to emulate something very
similar to a print f in Java or a string
format. Okay, so let's go.
Well, first of all, I must say that the
example I'm going to explain to you in
this video can be seen in this URL.
Okay. So there you can download the code
and try something and try to make the
same as me. Okay. Well, let me open the
generator program. I have it here.
Multi RPL.
Okay.
Well, before we look at the code, you
already know that what data genen does
under the hood is basically call another
program or another procedure and it does
it several times during the process
passing different events each time like
start, give me a value, end, and it's
this program that decides what to do
with each event. Okay, so this program
that gets called is what we usually call
the generator and that's exactly what
multi- RPL is. Okay, well as you can see
uh this program is a bound procedure.
Okay, it is called through gen and it
does it doesn't work like a normal
program as I said before. Okay, at the
beginning this comment that is here you
can read it. Uh well it it explains the
convention that we have to follow if we
want to use the generator. We need a
data structure where uh the first sub
field is the template. Okay, we are
going to have a string with the
placeholders uh for example item or
price. Okay. Uh the second sub field is
going to be uh the the marker that is
the character that goes before and after
each placeholder. Okay. In this case, as
you can see, it is uh um this this
character a percentage. Okay.
And uh the rest of the sub fields uh are
the actual replacement values. Okay. We
can have as variable in our template as
we need. But remember if we are going to
have different variables then we'll need
a different data structure in in uh for
each call okay for each use of data gen
okay we'll see it later okay so now
let's look at the procedure itself uh as
you can see we are resing this parameter
okay this is a standard structure
defined in data gen support and it has a
field called event so depending on the
value of event. We can do different
things.
When the event is start as you can see
here, then we are uh allocating some
memory for state structure. Okay, this
is because the generator gets called
multiple times. So we need somewhere to
keep the result while we're building it
up. Okay,
when the event is scala value as you can
see here scala value well this is called
one spell sub field in our input
structure. So here uh we check the sub
field number if it is one uh that's our
template. So we have we save it into a
state result. Okay, if it is two as you
can see here that is our marker. So we
save it into state marker here. Okay.
And for uh anything else uh we build the
placeholder name marker plus the sub
field name in uppercase plus marker
again and we use scum and replace here
uh to replace this that placeholder in
state result with the real value. Okay.
Well and finally I have it here. If uh
the event is end, we copy the final
state result into the output handle
using uh this this uh procedure and we
free the memory we allocated at the
start. Okay. Well, that's it. Uh there's
nothing more to explain here. Uh this is
a completely generic engine and it
doesn't know anything about item or
price as in the example. It just loops
through whatever subfields you uh give
it. Okay.
Now let's uh now see how we actually use
this.
Well, let me now create a new program.
We're going to create a new program
here. Uh for example,
I have example one, I think. Okay.
Well, we're going to have as always a
full uh free program without cycle in
this case with only a main procedure. So
here I declare my data structure
that is going to be let me make it
bigger. uh for example price m message
that's going to be a qualify
structure
and we're going to have the message
with this type
we're going to have a marker
going to be this
but we can change it for a different
value. Okay. Um we are going to have an
item
and price
for example.
Okay. So as you can see the template is
the first sub field that is message.
Okay. The marker is this percentage and
then we have item and price that are
going to replace item and price in the
template. Okay. So
let's now declare a pable to uh save the
output.
And now we're going to use uh our
structure uh to fill it with our
template and the values for the item and
price in this case. Okay. So we are
going to have uh
price message dot
message is going to be
the price of item.
item
between the two markers. Okay. Is
price. Okay.
Okay. This is going to be our our
template in this case.
And now
first message.
We're going to write two messages in in
our case. Okay.
My item is going to be for example
shirt.
Our price
is going to be
this.
And what we have to do now is this data
gen price message
data output. Okay, where I'm going to
save our result and our generator is
going to be
this. Okay, mold mold RP. Okay,
let's now make another uh call. For
example, second message.
Now we're going to have for example cap
a uh price that's going to be in this
case 1250.
And again data gen
price message data
output
and our the generator is going to be
this. Of course we can we're going to
send the message that we are getting
output
in this uh in this case
and also here. So we going we're going
to get uh both messages in our uh in our
job lock. Okay.
Okay. So let me now of course of course
we have to
compile
both programs. Okay.
Okay. The generator is compiled. We
don't have to we don't need to uh
compile it again. Compile it again.
Okay. Because uh we're going to use it
but we don't have to change it anymore.
Okay.
And now let's compile this uh example.
Okay. It is compiled correctly.
And now let's try to run it.
Let me change this.
So we going to look for it example
and call program.
And what we are getting is as you can
see
the price of item shirt is 1995
and the price of item cap is$1250.
as we
have in our program here.
Okay. So, it is uh working uh fine.
Okay. Very nice. Uh notice something
important here. The size of the output
this um and the size of the message that
is this uh have to be big enough for the
final text otherwise it gets truncated
sidedly without an error. So that's
something to keep in mind. Okay.
Well, so now the here's the interesting
part. If you worked with Java, you
probably now uh you probably know a
string format or print f uh where you
have one template string and you just
plug in as many values as you want.
Okay, this is basically the same idea
but instead of positional parameters
like uh percentage a percentage s or
percentage d we use name placeholder and
the arguments are just sub fields of a
data structure. So let's let's now
extend our example. Uh I want to add a
second price for example a sale price.
So we are going to have a
sale here.
Okay. And but let me remove this with
we're going to make only an example. And
now we're going to change our message.
We're going to have the price of item
item is price
but now
in sales is
save. Okay,
the marker is going to be the same. And
now, as you can see, we have one, two,
three different uh variables inside the
uh template. So we have to have item the
price and for this item we're going to
have say a price of for example uh 12.
Okay,
let me
change this.
And let me now compile it and run it.
Notice I didn't touch the generator
program at all. I just added a new sub
field called sale and a new placeholder
here in the template. That's it. Okay.
So, let's compile it.
Okay. It is compiled correctly. And if
we run it,
run action core program.
What we are getting is this the price of
item shirt is 1995 but now in sales is
12. Okay.
So it works correctly uh without
changing our motive RPL generator. Okay.
We can change this uh the way we want
and we don't have to change the uh uh
generator at all. Okay.
So to summarize, data gen together with
a generic generator like multi RPL gives
us a pretty elegant way to build
formated strings very similar to print f
or string format in other languages but
using a plain RPG data structure. Okay,
I hope you liked this video. Please like
if so and don't forget to subscribe to
the channel. And as always, thanks for
watching.